it's the oerman report and now here is
investigator it
oerman okay welcome to the oerman report
I am your host private investigator at
oerman tonight we have again forget it
tonight's a blockbuster show we have
John
kiru and uh he is a former CIA agent and
he's the author of The Reluctant spy and
uh he pretty much just got out of prison
uh for uh being like a whistleblower uh
so John are you there I sure am thanks
for having me thank you so much I'm
really excited to have you on here uh
especially the little chat we had off
the air uh so give us an idea who is
John caraku and and what is your story
well um I joined the CIA in January of
1990 as an analyst working on the Middle
East and uh loved that job uh did it for
seven and a half years and then decided
I was ready for something new and I
switched to operations also within the
CIA and uh did that for another seven
and a half years so after the September
11th attacks I became the chief of CIA
uh counterterrorism operations in
Pakistan and in that capacity led a raid
on the night of March 28th 2002 that
turned out to be the biggest
counterterrorism raid in CIA history
which still stands we captured out a
beta who we believed at the time was the
number three in al-Qaeda and we caught
51 other Al-Qaeda Fighters I went home
from Pakistan in uh in late
2002 and was asked when I got home if I
wanted to be certified in the use of
what they called uh enhanced
interrogation techniques I called them
torture techniques and I declined to be
trained uh I left the CIA in 2004 went
into the private sector for a while then
I went to the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee and I was the senior
investigator for that committee and I
was the senior intelligence adviser to
the chairman John KY uh but in 2007 I
went on ABC News and um and I said three
things that really changed the course of
my life I said that the CIA was
torturing its prisoners I said that
torture was official US government
policy and I said that that policy had
been approved and signed by the
president now the President George W
bush had said earlier in the week with
his eyes right on the camera he said we
do not torture and I said that the
president is a liar and so that resulted
in a four-year long uh FBI investigation
I was finally charged with five felonies
uh including three counts of Espionage
for uh saying that we were torturing
prisoners uh those espach counts were
dropped I took a plea to a lesser charge
I did 23 months in a federal prison not
in a country club prison but in a real
honest to God prison and um and got out
this
February how old are you now I'm 51 just
turned 51 wow 51 okay that's not easy
time going into 30 months in prison 47
years no no not not easy time at all and
I'll tell you what you know my only
exposure to prison had been watching
MSNBC at 11:00 at night um so I I really
didn't know what to ECT and and I
thought I was going to a minimum
security Work Camp uh that's what the
judge had recommended that's what the
prosecutors had agreed to uh in fact the
the Bureau of Prisons does whatever it
uh it pleases and so uh as soon as I
arrived they they took me around to the
back and put me in the actual prison
rather than in the minimum security Camp
yeah sometimes when I'm watching Rachel
mattow I feel like I'm in maximum
security I'm sorry I can't watch those
shows anymore okay so you just got out
now uh how old were you when you went
into the
CIA um I was young let's see I was
25 when I joined the CIA and what' you
do before that um I was in grad school I
I got a Bachelor's degree in in uh
Middle Eastern studies and I was working
on a on a master's degree in legislative
affairs when one of my professors uh who
liked my writing style uh asked me to
stay after class one day and uh to make
a long story short it turned out he was
actually undercover as a professor he
was working as what used to be called a
CIA spotter looking for grad students
who would fit into the agency's culture
and so um he recruited me into the CIA
right out of graduate
school you know there must be a lot of
that because I know I've had another
I've had a lot of CIA guys on the show
and uh uh I I believe I've heard that
story before that they were recruited
Yeah by a professor yeah it actually to
be quite common it it really you know
until
1992 or 93 with the passage of the Equal
Employment Opportunity Act it was pretty
much the only real way to get into the
CIA you had to be noticed you had to be
spotted I mean it's like it's like being
at the soda fountain at whatever that
famous uh drugstore was in Hollywood you
know if you wanted to be an actor so um
you know there there used to be senior
Cia officers under cover at important
universities all around the country and
I just you know was lucky enough to to
have one as my grad school adviser now
so but now but you had no plans uh even
though you were taking these foreign
languages uh you had no plans to go to
the CIA or something like that no I was
thinking that I I would probably end up
on Capitol Hill or maybe take the
foreign service exam I knew I wanted to
work in foreign affairs uh doing
something but I hadn't really given the
CIA any thought until they approached me
okay gotcha now now you said you were at
first you were an analyst or something
like that yeah I was for the first half
of my career and the the analytic jobs
at the CIA are a lot of fun if
especially if you're an introvert
because you're going to sit in your
cubicle nine or 10 hours a day and think
the big thoughts and write important
papers and send those papers to the
White House and hope that the president
reads them and comments on them um but
you know after doing that year in year
out working on Iraq you know year after
year after year it it wears you down and
I I thought boy I'm I'm 30 years old
there's got to be more than more to the
life than this so uh I decided you know
I I spoke Arabic I spoke Greek and um it
was time for something exciting and so
on the strength of those two languages I
was able to switch over to
counterterrorism
operations and this around 30 years old
now so you must been in pretty good
shape right yeah I I was in pretty good
shape I wasn't a former military but I I
was thin and young and strong and happy
to jump out of the plane and be trained
and everything else and you know the
friends of mine were like are you sure
you want to do this this is going to be
rough this is going to be like being in
the military at least through training
and I said yeah I know yeah I can I can
tough it out for whatever it was six or
eight months at the time and I ended up
doing very well and I enjoyed it very
much a and cuz right cuz the operations
you were doing as part of the CIA we're
actually military combat operations
right well no um they became military or
paramilitary combat operations after
September 11th before September 11th it
was you know much more old schooled it
was much more
sophisticated uh where you we have
something called the asset recruitment
cycle it's it's every officer has to
spot assess develop and recruit um an
agent in order to get promoted right you
have to recruit spies to steal secrets
and you spot these people depending on
what your target is or what kind of job
you're doing at diplomatic cocktail
parties or wherever I mean any number of
of different scenarios after September
11th it really did change to to
paramilitary operations where you know
you're you're wearing whatever special
forces where and you parachute into
something and you shoot the place up and
you grab the guy but before September
11th that's really not what the CIA was
right before it sounds more like Amway
or like you're recruiting people to come
in underneath you but you know pretty
much it was the same idea now you have
to establish a a relationship with
somebody with your target right you have
to establish a rapport um to the point
where you become so close to that person
or at least that person thinks that
you're close uh to the point where he's
going to commit Espionage for you he's
going to commit treason for you because
he likes you I mean there's certainly
other motivators money Revenge
ideology but the real basis of the
relationship is
friendship wow it's it's almost like
you're a con man or a cult you know I
I've
said years in interviews that that those
of us who were in operations or are in
operations uh right now you you're
trained to l and you lie every day and
you lie all day and you live a lie you
just have to know when to turn it off at
the end of the day a lot of guys can't
and so you know the CIA has a Sky High
divorce rate um but uh yeah you you are
very well trained as a professional
liar okay fascinating okay so now uh and
you said that you you went you went to
Afghanistan and you captured this guy
who was this guy you captured in in
Pakistan this was I was beta we thought
at the time that he was the number three
in al-Qaeda in fact he had never
actually joined Al-Qaeda but his job was
to provide al-qaeda's um logistical
support logistical leadership he created
al-qaeda's two training camps in
southern Afghanistan um if you needed a
false passport or you needed a plane
ticket Abu zua was the guy if you needed
a safe house or way to uh to get from
point A to point B across the border you
went to Abu Zeda so although he had
never formally joined Al-Qaeda he had
never pledged Fieldy to AMA Bin Laden he
was al-qaeda's go-to guy for
Logistics that's interesting so now but
you hear these stories over here in the
United States that they're hanging out
in caves and stuff like that yeah not
true okay then give us I I don't know
how that rumor ever got started that
they were living in caves that the whole
Cave Story never made sense to me
because I mean these guys are just like
everybody else you can you can r for for
only so long you people used to ask me
where do you think Bin Laden is and I
said I used to say I think Bin Laden is
comfortable in a house in a major city
somewhere and I'll tell you why because
these guys always thought that we
thought that they were hiding in the
tribal areas because we can't get to the
tribal areas except with the use of
drones in fact we knew that they were
all in major cities and it was this
reverse reverse
psychology so when they're in this
cities thinking that we're looking for
them in the countryside they tend to be
a little bit more sloppy especially with
their electronic communications cell
phones emails stuff like that and then
they're easier to catch when they're in
the city I mean we caught Abu Zeda in a
major city we caught khed shik Muhammad
in a major city he was The Mastermind of
the 911 attacks we caught uh ABD in a
major city he was The Mastermind of the
coal bombing we caught Ramsey Ben in
major city and then of course you know
Bin Laden was in the Pakistani version
of West Point in a major city yeah right
now now what do you make of that you
know because uh you'd think that these
guys would be on our side right or on
your side you know on the CIA side uh
well you I always said that the
Pakistani intelligence service isi was
really two separate organizations the
the guys that I was working with were
were just fantastic I mean they were all
trained in the UK uh they all went
through Sandhurst and British police
training and they were really great they
were great counterterrorism Partners but
isi is also the same organization that
created the Taliban you know when when
Benazir buo was the Prime Minister of
Pakistan she created the Taliban see
Taliban is a word in both Arabic and in
Udu that means uh students the the
singular is Talib and the plural is
Taliban which means students and these
students were studying in madrasas in
Islamic private Islamic schools in
Pakistan and they were they were Afghan
Nationals so the pakistanis were running
trucks across Afghanistan to Iran so
that they could sell their goods in Iran
and the um trucks were being hijacked as
they were crossing Pakistan so benzir B
got this group of students together and
said I want you to ride along in the
trucks you know with weapons and if
anybody tries to hijack the trucks fight
them off so as these trucks would cross
Afghanistan the Taliban were able to
secure individual uh villages along the
Route and that's how they ended up
taking over Pakistan so Benz zerbo and
isi created the Taliban they trained the
Taliban they financed the Taliban they
arms the Taliban and at the same time
other isi officers are working with us
to fight the Taliban so there was this
disconnect within the Pakistani
intelligence service you could trust
some of them you couldn't trust others
you just had to play your cards
well okay now I I recall I forget who
was president at the time but I I recall
that the Taliban com to the United
States and it was like a big press
conference and and it was revealed that
their lobbyist was the daughter of one
of the CIA directors they familiar with
that
story yeah I do remember that story and
I I recall she was based in New Jersey I
think it was do you remember which CIA
CIA director that was yeah I don't but I
I recall it being sort of a non
controversial issue at the time because
you know we we never had any beef with a
Taliban historically and some of those
members of the Taliban especially the
older ones were jihadis from the from
the
the war against the Soviets and of
course we we financed them we trained
them we armed them we gave them Stinger
missiles and every year or two they
would come to the United States they
would meet with President Reagan they
would be FedEd in Washington and they'd
go back to uh to Afghanistan so we had
this relationship with at least some of
these these people and until Bin Laden
went to
Afghanistan we sort of saw the Taliban
is not our fight if if they were trample
women's rights well you know we had no
National interest there it was none of
our business it wasn't until they
provided safe haven for bin Laden that
we decided this was going to be a
problem what do you make of Bin Laden
okay some people say that outright that
he was CIA and they had I think his name
was Osman or something like that Ben
Osman you know they had another name you
know yeah and that
uh and then you got all this stuff about
how um his brothers connected up with
the the Carlile group and was actually
meeting with bush the the day of 911 oh
oh sure but but that's not scandalous
That's Not Unusual first of all Bin
Laden was never trained by the CIA he
was never a CIA Source he was never
armed by the CIA he didn't actually go
to Afghanistan from Saudi Arabia until
after the CIA um stopped funding and
training uh the Afghan mujahedin so
that's kind of a common misn
a lot of people think that the CIA
trained Bin Laden or created Bin Laden
that's just not true um you're talking
about the extended Bin Laden family the
bin Laden family is a very honorable
family in Saudi Arabia they're
incredibly wealthy you know 10 figure
kind of wealthy because the old man
abdurahman Bin Laden who originally
moved to Saudi Arabia from Yemen um
created what became the Kingdom's
largest construction firm and and his
firm would make would would do the
biggest projects they would build
airports and and hospitals and ports and
shopping malls and stuff like that
so the old man insisted that that most
if not all of his uh children be
educated in the west um they travel to
the United States all the time they own
property in Beverly Hills and in Miami
Beach and you know they're very
Americanized it's just that that one son
Osama was for whatever reason
radicalized and instead of going into
the family business along with his 113
other
brothers um he he went to Afghanistan to
make
Jihad and and and what do you make of uh
people who say well he he died prior to
the to the story that U that we hear in
the news about yeah that's just nonsense
I mean you know we we we would get these
reports at the CIA all the time that Bin
Laden had kidney failure he was on
dialysis inside a cave uh he had some
kind of spinal disorder we were always
getting these these uh medical uh rumors
reported back to us and and none of them
ended up uh to be true but no he he was
in perfectly fine Health except for some
arthritis um he had an ongoing hip
problem um but he he was he was healthy
enough to wage war against the United
States until the day died
okay
um oh boy oh okay I almost
forgot St my mind for a second what what
do you make of these stories about the
the the Navy Seals uh who are part of
that operation now all of a sudden
they're all dead in U in helicopter
crashes and stuff right you know that's
actually not uncommon um being a Navy
SEAL is one of the most dangerous
professions in the world and um we're
not talking specifically about the Navy
Seals who were directly uh involved in
the bin Laden takedown being killed
we're talking about Navy Seals from
their broader unit so we're talking
about you know 100 120 150 seals so for
for a number of seals a high number of
seals to be killed um whether it's in
accidents or in combat is actually very
sadly uh
common okay so ni so you're saying that
the when we hear these stories about how
the Navy Seals who killed Bin Laden now
most of them are dead it's you're saying
it's not the actual same guys it's just
the guys in the same no not at all okay
it's not the same guys uhuh
interesting okay um yeah let me
interrupt you you know when when people
talk about SEAL Team Six um or you see
SEAL Team Six in movies you you imagine
a dozen or dozen half guys that make up
SEAL Team Six in fact it's several
hundred guys that make up SEAL Team
Six and it's you know from those several
hundred U that that we find these these
individuals who have been killed in
accidents or killed in
combat now what about uh the stories
about the the funeral like this this
ocean funeral and then even some uh
congressmen who saw pictures and stuff
like that said it looked like it was
fake and and then even the White House
had to kind of step back on some of the
official story around that what do you
make of that yeah you know I don't know
what believe I I think he probably was
buried at Sea the way they they say he
was buried at Sea maybe some of the
details are wrong cuz God knows the
White House's story changes constantly
uh every time this comes up but I I
don't I just don't see any conspiracy
related to it I I see a bunch of people
talking out of school and and pretending
to know the details of what happened
when in fact they don't really know the
details and I think that's why the story
tends to change but I do think that Bin
Laden was killed uh in whatever it was
May of 2011 I think he really was buried
at Sea um and I I'm just not sure that
the details are really that important
now now how about when you were in CIA
were you ever involved in like a a
promoting false stories and and uh no
you know I there there is such a thing
as a false flag operation false flag
operations are very very um difficult
and there are a lot of moving parts and
you have to have a lot of people would
buy into the conspiracy um but but we
really didn't use those very often
because they were so complicated it
wasn't until you know just
recently you know where people have
started to email me or Facebook me or
contact me on Twitter about false flag
operations and you I even have one
friend who just thinks that every event
in life is a false flag operation and
it's just it just seems so Preposterous
to me because they are so labor in
ensive and so difficult to carry out
that just doesn't make sense to me yeah
I I I sympathize with you I get those
emails
too they mean well they really do but I
know and you kind of can't blame some
people for being paranoid you know you
can't blame people with being parent no
you can't you know when when you have a
government that's not transparent right
when you have a government that that
pretends to tell the American people the
whole story uh related to these to these
terrorist uh you know operations and
then the story changes you can't blame
people for being for being suspicious of
the government line right right and and
you said now we have a government that
tortures people and says it's okay
exactly and that denied it and denied it
and denied it you know I said this I
said this the other day in an oped that
I wrote everything that the government
has told us about torture since 2002 has
been a lie so why would you believe them
now you know George W bush said in 2002
we don't torture
and he said it again in three and four
and five and six and seven that the week
that I went on ABC News he looked right
in the camera and he said we do not
torture and I remember saying to my wife
that is a bald-faced
lie he's just lying to the American
people and George Tennant said the same
thing in 2005 on 60 Minutes he came off
in that segment like he was unhinged he
was practically shouting it we don't
talk torture we don't torture we don't
torture well of course we
torture and what makes it worse is not
only are there us laws that that
prohibit
torture but there are international
treaties and conventions that the US is
a signatory to and in some cases that
the US
wrote and bullied other countries into
signing and then we violate those
International treaties and conventions
by torturing let me tell you another
thing in January of 1968 The Washington
Post ran a front- page photograph of a
of an American Soldier waterboarding a
North Vietnamese prisoner when that
photo was published the Secretary of
Defense Robert mcamera um ordered an
investigation the soldier was arrested
and he was charged with torture and he
was convicted and sent to prison so why
was torture illegal in
1968 but it wasn't illegal in 20 200 2
cu the law didn't change there was no
there was no Amendment to the law
Banning torture saying well okay now
it's okay you know there was no law that
said well water boarding is not torture
cold cells not torture sleep
deprivations not torture the law didn't
change but we just had a group of
attorneys in the Justice Department who
decided that they were going to twist
the law uh to do what they wanted and
that's exactly what happened yeah this
is really you know you and I are the
same age you know uh and and this this
is such a a disturbing uh that even that
we're even talking about this and and
that people are excusing it and uh it's
really uh shattering it is it is you
know I I I consider myself to be a
patriot and not just a patriot but a
patriot who who spent 20 years serving
my country in some of the most awful and
dangerous places on Earth and I know
that my country is better than this my
country shouldn't be waterboarding
people or or forcing hummus up their
rectums or murdering them in the middle
of of uh interrogations or to make
matters worse droning American citizens
overseas who have not been charged with
a crime who have not had the right to
meet their accusers in court that's not
the America that I know and love I don't
know where this came from okay well then
then coming from where you are right now
today and and just having served 30
months I believe right 30 months yes do
you still consider yourself a patriot do
you still support the Iraq War the
Afghanistan war do you still uh where
are you now well I I am a patriot I
never I never supported the Iraq War
though I never thought that was a just
war and I even spent a good amount of uh
space in my in my first book about it U
that was a war of choice that was a war
of venge for the Bush family uh but yeah
I I always supported the Afghan War I
don't anymore because because the the
whole point of the Afghan war was to
defeat Al-Qaeda and we defeated Al-Qaeda
by the middle of 2003 so the rest of
this since 2003 this has been nation
building which is never a good idea but
yeah I I am still a patriot and I want
my September 10th country back
and ruined by by George W bush and by
Barack Obama equally what about the
overthrow in
Libya see this is another thing Gaddafi
was a was a very bad guy but we actually
had a very healthy working relationship
with with Qaddafi and Qaddafi hated
Al-Qaeda as much as we did so flipping
sides at the last minute like we did to
overthrow kadashi was a was a terrible
policy error I mean look at the place
now it's it's literally Anarchy it's
chaos right well you say it's a policy
area but according to Wesley Clark he
says that's the plan all along is to
cause D stabilization to cause chaos see
this is the thing and and West Clark I
mean West Clark was a fourstar general
um he ought to know U what he's talking
about so I if that's if that's the
policy I think that's an incredibly
short-sighted policy because invariably
where there's a power vacuum we get
dragged in and when we get dragged into
something like this like we did in
Lebanon for example in the 1980s we
can't get ourselves back out again
do do you think there's a motive to get
us back out when the when these
companies like Hal Burton are making all
this money on laundry and and it just
it's unbelievable the kind of money
they're making over there that that's a
really important point I never believed
that until I'm going to say the last
four or five years and I I've come to
the conclusion that that we need
economically we need for war to be a
permanent thing yeah and already the
American people are sort of numb to the
idea of War
in part because we have an all volunteer
military uh and I think that's why we're
not seeing demonstrations in the streets
I mean already Afghanistan it's the
longest war in American history it's
twice as long more than actually it's
more than well now it's it's three times
as long as World War II was and uh you
know nobody's really upset about
this so now John where did
um the torture ing get started was this
at Guantanamo was this in Abu gra where
did you it it was before Abu gra and um
actually before Guantanamo uh ABA was
the first
highlevel uh Al-Qaeda related prisoner
that we had captured and
so you know at the time and when I say
at the time I mean I mean immediately
after the September 11th attacks Osama
Bin Laden released a statement in which
he said that Al-Qaeda was planning
another attack that would dwarf
September 11th and we were panicked at
the thought because September 11th was a
was a disaster it was an intelligence
failure it was just an an across
theboard you know American failure so we
were worried about this this what they
call the ticking Time Bomb
scenario and
so cia's leadership believed that Abu
Zeda had information related to whatever
this upcoming attack was or was going to
be in fact there there was no upcoming
attack uh he just said it to panic us
and and he
succeeded so a decision was made at CIA
headquarters that we were going to come
up with these with these torture
techniques it was a list of of something
like 10 different torture techniques and
um and they sent this list to the
justice department which approved it and
then it went to the lawyers at the
National Security Council they approved
it from there it went to the um National
Security adviser who was she was cond
condesa rice at the time she approved it
and sent it to the president well nobody
in the cia's leadership thought the
president was going to approve this
because it was clearly torture and sure
enough he approved it and I remember
sitting in a meeting with the deputy
director of the CIA um the day after the
memo the signed memo came into
headquarters and the deputy director
said something like three times during
the course of our conversation I can't
believe the president signed that memo I
can't believe it and that's how the
torture regime started
Guantanamo I mean we we really didn't
even how should I say that Guantanamo
was supposed to be a temporary stop see
we were we were capturing people so
quickly and we were capturing so many of
them especially after the fall of torab
Bora in October 2001 that we needed
someplace to just park them long enough
uh for us to put all the paperwork
together and then send them to the
United States to stand trial because
September 11th was still an ongoing open
criminal investigation guantan was never
supposed to be permanent they were
supposed to stay there only long enough
for us to then send them onward to the
states for uh for trial and of course
nobody ever went on trial and here we
are 14 years later and we're still
talking about whether or not we should
close
Guantanamo you know my next guest
tonight uh Michael uh bo the attorney uh
and and the story is about how the
Marines turned a blind eye to child sex
abuse did you ever run across any of
that over there yeah in Afghanistan you
actually run into it with some
regularity it's this weird thing in
Afghan culture that if a boy um
does not yet have whiskers if he hasn't
yet reached puberty um you can have sex
with him uh it's specific to to um Sunni
Muslims and uh that's why a lot of a lot
of Taliban uh would would rape young
boys it's just this weird perverted
cultural thing that they have what about
the stories we heard of of uh young boys
being raped at Abu gra in front of their
parents as part of
interrogation um to the best of my
understanding that didn't happen
although I mean it's almost as bad uh
it's my understanding that some of our
soldiers threatened prisoners with that
that if you don't talk we're going to
rape your children if you don't talk
we're going to rape your your wife or
we're going to rap rape your children in
front of your wife we'll rape your wife
in front of you you know that kind of
thing now that that's also a violation
of law both US law and and uh the um
United Nations convention on torture uh
but we we actually did that kind of
thing in Abu grave at least threatened
it I mean well if you look at some of
the pictures that came out of Abu have
you been to Abu grave what do you know
firstand no no I've not been to ABRA
okay but you you've seen some of those
pictures that came out of there oh yeah
they horrific naked guys and naked guys
in a pyramid you know it's Way Beyond
the naked guys with electrical wires
attached to their scrotums you know we
we did horrible things to people over
there so whatever hor things that that
aren't that aren't appropriate in any
circumstance whether in war or peace or
even effective to get uh confessions out
of people and really that's the most
important point they're not effective in
any way in getting confessions or in
getting any kind of intelligence you
know we know now from both the Senate
torture report and the CIA inspector
General's report that was released in
the spring of 2009 that torture never
worked that that CIA interrogators never
gathered any actionable intelligence and
that no American lives were saved and
and let me add one more thing about that
too you hear a lot of people now saying
well it was just the Senate intelligence
committee Democrats that signed on to
that report let me remind those
naysayers that the Senate Democrats and
the Senate intelligence committee
investigators used primary source
documents that is original CIA
intelligence cables from the field to
write that report so there is no
rebuttal you know there is no excuse
torture didn't work it never works it
didn't save any American
lives did you watch the hearings
yesterday I did okay so did I the whole
thing all day long now now what do you
make of that it seems to me that
something more was going on down there
with the CIA compound across from this
uh you know you've heard the rumors
right about gun running and these kind
of things what do you make of that yeah
I think there's actually uh some
evidence of gun
running yeah you know this this whole
idea of gun running um has been a
problem really since the very beginning
of the uprising against
Gaddafi already already Libya is kind of
a No Man's Land because it's its borders
aren't clearly defined the desert is
constantly shifting Libya is an
intensely tribally based society so you
can't really you know people in Libya
never really trust their central
government and then you've got vast
numbers of weapons uh changing hands so
you know who's involved I'm not sure
we're ever going to really get to the
bottom of that story was the CIA
involved were the British involved were
the Egyptians involved I don't think
we'll ever really
know and it doesn't seem like that these
hearings are even trying to find
out yeah you know there are so many
legitimate issues that we could be
talking about related to Benghazi or or
Libya more broadly um and instead it
just devolved into this this political
thing between Hillary Clinton and the
Republicans on the committee I don't
think anybody did the American people
any service by allowing this to become
political when there are some very
important intelligence issues at play
here and you know I I saw a thing on the
news the other day saying that in the
years that George W Bush was was
president something like 60 attacks
there were 60 attacks around the world
against American embassies and
consulates including I forget what you
know half a dozen or a dozen deaths and
we've never investigated any of those
maybe we should maybe we should
investigate every time there's an attack
on a on an American Embassy or consulate
or anytime American Personnel overseas
are killed it shouldn't be political it
shouldn't be partisan it should be
something we're doing so that we can
improve the protection of our own
facilities and our own people yeah there
were half a dozen EMB attacks that
weekend it was demonstrations but they
breached reg yeah so yeah why aren't we
why aren't we investigating that well a
good question you know it's a circus
that's why look at Donald Trump we gotta
wait all that all that it's a circus
over there right now man that's right I
wish it would torture me I wish I can't
take any more of this what do you make
of uh we just had this thing in the news
just in the past week with this guy this
Fox news commentator was claiming to be
a CIA what's going on with that man you
know it's funny to me I have run into so
many people over the years who claim to
be agency right and um and you can spot
them from a mile away because they they
get the lingo wrong uh I interviewed a
guy one time he I was working in the
private sector after I left the CIA and
I was working um in competitive
intelligence business intelligence and
so this guy applied for a job and on his
resume he said he was a CIA officer and
I thought oh okay well I'm going to I'm
going to take this guy to lunch and uh
you know maybe we have some friends in
common I'll see if he's any good so I
took him to lunch and I said to him
listen I said it's it's not clear from
your resume whether you were from the
director of operations or the director
of intelligence uh so where did you work
and he said oh both I was I was both and
I said well that's kind of impossible
you have to be from one or the other oh
he says I was operations I said oh okay
uh so where did you work he said oh I
was counter terrorism I said well that's
great I was counter terrorism what
division were you in and he just looked
at me with this blank this
blank and I said you made all this up
didn't you and he's like I'm really
sorry I really need this job and I said
okay thanks nice meeting you and that
was the end of it so this guy on Fox
News you know he said he was like
something like outside paramilitary
Special Operations well those are just
meaningless words there is no such
position as outside paramilitary Special
Operations I mean it it sounds like very
woo very intriguing and it's it's all
these buzzwords but it but it doesn't
mean anything there is no such position
and so you know the first time I heard
this guy say I thought absolutely no way
he's CIA he may have been a contractor
you know he may have been inflating what
he did but there's no this guy was CIA
and then sure enough he
wasn't okay but now first how do you get
away with
that you know it's why doesn't the CIA
step in right away and say this guy's
not the he's not the real
deal yeah he's not the real deal the the
real shame about this whole thing is
that apparently this son of a gun was
able to trick people at at DOD into
giving him a security clearance just
because he told them he had been CIA
this guy went overseas to Afghanistan
stand to advise our generals on strategy
because he said he was from the CIA well
I can tell you any CIA officer I've ever
worked with could peg this guy in five
seconds and say this guy's making the
whole thing up well okay you know we
spend a lot of money to support the CIA
right yeah do they have TV
sets do they have cable news couldn't
they turn on their TV over there and see
this guy on TV and say hey does anybody
know this guy yeah and we do that right
like every once in a while if I'm
flipping through Fox News I'll see
somebody like well I won't even say his
name but I'll see somebody I I served
with and I'm like oh hey he ended up on
Fox news good for him or else I saw I
saw a former boss of mine on CNBC and I
was like oh hey there's Mike he's on
CNBC good for Mike but this guy I mean
you would think that somebody would say
you know gez I'm paramilitary CIA I
never saw this guy before or or even
active duty right now CIA would they
must be checking to see what information
slipping out through Fox News or through
the news you think yeah you would think
I I would have you're you're exactly
right I would have expected somebody at
the CIA to call Fox News and say hey
this guy's an impostor and especially
when we know for a fact that the
intelligence uh departments have a lot
of control over what goes on in the
media and the news and movies absolutely
yeah I got some guys here I'm working
with Pierce Redmond and Tom Seer they
they they get the F records of how the
military and the defense department is
so involved in the movie industry into
such detail you wouldn't believe it's
embarrassing yeah so now how did this
guy get away with this for so long I
don't know it's I I hope that this is an
anomaly no it's I hope that somehow for
whatever reason this guy slipped through
the cracks I will add though that his
message on Fox News was always solidly
pro- CIA solidly Pro dood and I wonder
if people at the CIA did know that he
was an impostor but figured well you
know he's saying all the right things so
we're not going to
object okay yeah because because I you
know in my business I run into a lot of
these guys who make these kind of claims
in my business as a pi and also as radio
host I run into these crackpots all day
long you know and some of them are radio
host and I don't understand how uh
they're getting away with this I worked
with a guy in the private sector who I I
never met anybody who so desperately
wanted to be a CIA officer as this guy
and so he finally got himself u in as a
contractor and I said to him so what are
you doing over there anyway and he says
well uh it's it's it's pretty Hush Hush
but it's a special intel Ops support uh
special weapons and tactics and and I'm
like dude you make yourself sound like a
fool yeah because none of those words
mean
anything and you get that a lot
especially in Washington it's pretty sad
yeah I hear you I hear you I people they
try to talk this lingo you know it's
just boots on the ground you know
exactly all the buzzword and the and the
catchphrases oh
man you know we that's like the last
nine minutes you know what do you want
to leave us with give us some advice
here well one thing that I'm really that
I'm really upset about uh since
September 11th and and this is something
that I I write about a lot I take very
seriously and it's the loss of our civil
liberties the civil liberties of
individual Americans in the name of
National
Security when I first uh joined the CIA
we had several rules that were written
in stone and that was that the CIA did
not spy on Americans and that's the NSA
did not spy on Americans and if for
example if the NSA had accidentally
stumbled on to an American who had
accidentally um intercepted a telephone
call every trace of that interception
had to be purged from nsa's records and
then NSA had to inform Congress oh my
God we've accidentally intercepted the
phone call or the email of an American
citizen well now nsa's primary targets
are American
citizens NSA just built a a a new
facility in the desert in Utah that has
enough storage space to save every every
phone call every text message and every
email from Every American for the next
500 years we have the CIA droning
American citizens overseas as I said
earlier who have never been charged with
a crime who have never been able to face
their accusers in a court of law and uh
and there just doesn't seem to be any
outrage over this if if the the
government can kill uh you know an
American citizen overseas then can the
government kill an American citizen you
know on his Ranch in
Idaho we don't know and the Attorney
General of the United States at least
the the previous one uh Eric Holder
wouldn't even answer that question when
when asked it by uh Senator Rand Paul so
I'm just seeing a real Devolution in our
civil liberties and uh I think it's a
very U
dangerous uh
Trend yeah and the government whether or
not they they they're killing people you
know off the street they they definitely
are throwing people in prison off the
street yeah they sure are and you can
testify firsthand and I got to tell you
a good number of my guests on this show
have been to prison you know uh and it
just seems to be a recurring I got
former guests that are in prison right
now you know for for nonsense again
Liberty kind of stuff you know yeah yeah
good grief I'll tell you I was charged
under the Espionage Act because I had
had a conversation with a with a
reporter from The New York Times and I
said that we were torturing prisoners so
that bought me three Espionage counts um
the Espionage Act was written in
1917 to Target German sabur during the
first world war between 1917 and 2009 it
was used three times but since Barack
Obama became president it's been used
nine times against Americans now none of
us none of us have been accused of of
passing information to a foreign
government to an enemy these were all
for um information that uh that went to
the press and for several of us and I'm
thinking about you know myself and Tom
Drake for example from NSA and Jeffrey
Sterling from CIA it was after we had
either reported through the chain of
command or gone public with evidence of
waste fraud abuse illegality or a threat
to Public Health or safety that's the
definition of
whistleblowing so here we are near the
end of Barack Obama's uh second uh
second term and I can safely say I think
that Barack Obama is going to go down in
history as the enemy of transparency as
the enemy of of whistleblowing and of
transparent government and that's
exactly what he said he would not do
when elected president
okay that's a good question what do you
make of Barack Obama because a lot of
people I've had on this show that have
met him okay like cynthy mckenny and
Cindy shean and others uh including a a
former State Department guy who's a K
Street lobbyist right now okay uh and
when I ask them this question you know
because obviously his paperwork and his
background is suspect he doesn't have
the right paperwork do you make him to
be a
CIA
creation I've been very public with my
opinion on this and I'll tell you what I
think has
happened you had a a very Junior Senator
a very Junior first term Senator who had
no exposure to National Security uh no
experience in National Security at all
that's exactly the kind of young new
president the CIA wants because as soon
as that new president sees his first
blue border report or black border
report something that so many levels
Above Top Secret they can't even keep
track as soon as he's brought into his
first super secret
operation they have him hooked and
they've essentially recruited him and I
think that that is exactly what happened
to Barack Obama you know he campaigned
as an outsider he C campaigned on the
idea of of clean government and
transparency and as soon as they brought
him into the club they had
him there was a book that came out in
2014 by Halper and hman uh two reporters
Time Magazine and MSNBC they had done a
report or they had done a book rather on
the 2008 election and then they did a
follow-up book on the 2012 election and
there were two quotes from Barack Obama
in that second book that were really
chilling and Obama had agreed to uh to
an interview for the book so these came
right from the horse's mouth first he
said I never told anybody I was a
liberal and I thought that was just f
fting the second quote was I never had
any idea I would be so good at killing
people and with that he was talking
about the Drone program and and that
tells me that that's not how he went
into his
presidency it's how he changed once he
became
president it's very interesting but uh I
had a guest on here that discussed U
some of his previous employment and uh
he described it as a a classic CIA front
operation yeah but the CIA doesn't do
stuff like that I mean they they just
that's that's the stuff of movies and
fiction books that's just not how it
works okay and and and the history with
his parents and stuff like that and the
travels and associations with Communists
and that you don't see anything Suspect
with that either no I don't I mean
you're talking about about a plot that
would have
begun with with his birth
I mean I I don't know anybody that's
that smart or that's that good to be
able to carry out this conspiracy from
from the guy's birth all the way to the
presidency like a Manchurian
Candidate gotcha okay I I really want to
have you back um to to discuss the whole
story of Abu grabe you know and all that
kind of stuff just just specifically to
get into all the details on that just uh
uh 100% specifically but once again
what's your your website oh thanks my
website is uh
www.j kiraku Doom it's John J N kiraku
is k i r i a
k.com and we got the book reluctant spy
my secret life in a cia's war on terror
uh but you got a couple other books
you're working on too as well yeah um
I've got two books completed that are
out for bid right now one is called
letters from Loretto uh which um is
based on a series of blogs that I wrote
from prison and the second one or it's
the third one I guess um it's more fun
it's it's called do doing time like a
spy how the CIA taught me to survive and
thrive in prison okay listen you got to
promise me you're going to come back all
right I'd love to thanks for having okay
man that's good stuff we got to get into
that thank you so much for coming on my
friend oh it's my pleasure thanks a lot
good night bye-bye
[Music]
e
e for